<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sheets for poor families ... by Richard Baxter.</title>
            <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17569</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12323164</idno>
  <idno type="VID">59498</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248577855</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1441 (both pts.)</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1403 (pt. 2)</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6530</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12323164</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59498)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 269:6, 201:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sheets for poor families ... by Richard Baxter.</title>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 pts.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert White for Francis Tyton ... and for Nevill Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pt. 1 has subtitle: The first, instructions to the ungodly for their conversion; pt. 2 has special t.p. with title: Instructions for a holy life.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 201:18 (B1441) is complete work; copy at reel 269:6 (B1403) is pt. 2 only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59498:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59498:1"/>
                  <p> TWO SHEETS FOR Poor Families.</p>
                  <p>THE FIRST: Instructions to the Ungodly FOR THEIR CONVERSION.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert White,</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> at the three Daggers in <hi>Fleet-street:</hi> and for <hi>Nevill Simmons,</hi> Book-seller in <hi>Kederminster.</hi> 1665.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59498:2"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59498:2"/>
                  <head>Two Sheets for Poor Families.</head>
                  <head type="sub">I. Instructions to the Ungodly, For their CONVERSION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the saving of souls be a matter of unexpressible importance, yet (the Lord have mercy upon them,) what abundance are there that think it not worthy of their <hi>serious enquiry;</hi> nor <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. 36. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 33. <hi>Job</hi> 21. 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. 17. <hi>Psalm</hi> 1. 2, 3. <hi>Psalm</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12</note> the <hi>reading</hi> of a <hi>good Book,</hi> one hour in a week? For the sake of these careless <hi>slothfull</hi> sinners, I have here spoken <hi>much in a little room,</hi> that they may not refuse to read and consider so short a Lesson, unless they think their souls worth <hi>nothing!</hi> Sinner, as thou wilt shortly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer it before God, deny not to God, to thy self, and me, the sober pondering, and faithful practising, these few Directions.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:59498:3"/> I. <hi>Begin at home and Know thy self:</hi> Consider what <hi>it is to be a MAN.</hi> Thou art made a nobler Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then the <hi>Urutes. They</hi> serve <hi>thee,</hi> and are <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psal.</hi> 8. 4, 5, 6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26, 27. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 10.</note>
                     <hi>governed</hi> by thee; and Death ends all <hi>their</hi> pains and pleasures: But <hi>thou</hi> hast <hi>Reason</hi> to <hi>Rule thy self and them;</hi> to <hi>know thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>od,</hi> and <hi>foresee</hi> thy <hi>End,</hi> and <hi>know thy way,</hi> and <hi>do thy duty.</hi> Thy <hi>Reason,</hi> and <hi>Free-will,</hi> and <hi>Executive Power,</hi> are part of the <hi>Image of God</hi> upon thy <hi>nature:</hi> so is thy <hi>Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on</hi> over the <hi>Brutes,</hi> as (under him) thou art their <hi>Owner,</hi> their <hi>Ruler,</hi> and their <hi>End.</hi> But thy <hi>Holy Wisdome,</hi> and <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> and <hi>Ability</hi> is the chief part of his Image, on which thy <hi>Happiness</hi> depends. Thou hast a soul that cannot be <hi>satisfied in Knowing,</hi> till thy Knowledge reach to <hi>God himself:</hi> Nor can it be <hi>Disposed off</hi> by any other: Nor can it (or the societies of the world) be <hi>well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 17. 3. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 6, 7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 24.</note>
                     <hi>according to its nature,</hi> without regard to <hi>his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign authority,</hi> and without the <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> of <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Misery hereafter;</hi> nor can it be <hi>Happy</hi> in any thing, but <hi>Seeing,</hi> and <hi>Lovi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g</hi> and <hi>Delighting in this</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 4, 5. <hi>Psalm</hi> 16. 5. <hi>to</hi> 11. <hi>Isaiah</hi> 45. 18.</note>
                     <hi>God,</hi> as he is revealed in the other world. And is <hi>this Nature</hi> given thee <hi>in vain?</hi> If the nature of <hi>all things</hi> be fitted to its <hi>Ʋse</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> then it must needs be so with <hi>thine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. By <hi>Knowing thy self</hi> then, thou must needs know that <hi>there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s a GOD:</hi> and that he is <hi>thy Maker,</hi> and <hi>infinite in all perfections:</hi> and that he is thy <hi>Owner,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Psalm</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 19, 20. <hi>Psalm</hi> 46. 10. <hi>Psalm</hi> 9. 10. <hi>Psalm</hi> 100. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. <hi>Psalm.</hi> 19. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Psalm</hi> 47. 7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 25. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 6.</note> thy <hi>Ruler,</hi> and thy <hi>Felicity</hi> or <hi>End.</hi> He is mad that seeth not, that such <hi>creatures</hi> have a <hi>Cause</hi> or <hi>Maker,</hi> and that all the <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Wisdome,</hi> and <hi>Goodness</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> is caused by a <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Wisdome,</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> which is <hi>greater</hi> than that of all the world. And <hi>who</hi> can be our <hi>Owner▪</hi> but He that <hi>made us?</hi> And <hi>who</hi> can be our <hi>Highest Governour,</hi> but our <hi>Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner?</hi> whose Infinite <hi>Power, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sdome</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> maketh him only fit thereto? And if he be our <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,</hi> he must needs have <hi>Laws;</hi> with <hi>Rewards</hi> for the <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>Punishment</hi> for the <hi>bad;</hi> and must <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Execute</hi> accordingly. And <hi>if</hi> he be our <hi>Chiefest Benefactor,</hi> and all that we have is <hi>from him,</hi> and all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59498:3"/> our <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Happiness</hi> is <hi>in him,</hi> nothing can be more clear than that the very <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> doth prove, that in hope of future happiness he should <hi>absolutely</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 37. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5. 22. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 8, 9.</note>
                     <hi>resign himself</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>disposal</hi> of this God, and that he should <hi>absolutely obey him,</hi> and that he should <hi>Love and serve him</hi> with all his powers. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impossible to <hi>Love, obey</hi> and <hi>please</hi> that <hi>God</hi> too much, who is thus our <hi>Cause,</hi> our <hi>End,</hi> our <hi>All.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. By knowing thus <hi>thy self</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> it is easie to know what Primitive <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Godliness</hi> is: Even this <hi>hearty, entire and absolute resignation,</hi> of the <hi>soul to</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Titus</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. 16, 17, 18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>Psalm</hi> 100. <hi>Psalm</hi> 37. 4. <hi>Psalm</hi> 40. 8. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1, 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0, 21. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 18.</note>
                     <hi>God,</hi> as the <hi>Infinite Power, Wisdome and Goodness:</hi> as our <hi>Creator, our Owner, Governour,</hi> and <hi>felicity or End:</hi> fully <hi>submitting</hi> to his <hi>Disposals; Obeying</hi> his <hi>Laws,</hi> in <hi>Hope</hi> of his <hi>promised Rewards,</hi> and <hi>Fear of his threatened punishments;</hi> and <hi>Loving</hi> and <hi>Delighting in Himself</hi> and all his <hi>appearances</hi> in the world, and <hi>Desiring</hi> and <hi>seeking</hi> the <hi>endless sight</hi> and <hi>enjoyment</hi> of <hi>him</hi> in <hi>Heavenly Glory:</hi> and expressing these Affections in daily <hi>Prayer, Thanksgiving</hi> and <hi>Praise.</hi> This is the <hi>Use</hi> of all thy faculties: the end and business of thy life: the health and happiness of thy soul: This is that <hi>Holiness</hi> or <hi>Godliness</hi> which God doth so much call for.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. And by this it is easie to know, what a <hi>state of sin,</hi> and <hi>ungodliness</hi> is. Even the <hi>want</hi> of all <hi>this Holiness;</hi> and the setting up of <hi>Carnal-SELF</hi> instead <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 19. 13. <hi>John</hi> 3. 3, 5, 6. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 15, 16. <hi>Ro.</hi> 13. 13, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 16. <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14▪ 26. 33▪</note> of <hi>GOD.</hi> When men are <hi>proudly Great,</hi> and <hi>Wise,</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> in their own eyes; and would <hi>Dispose</hi> of <hi>themselves</hi> and all their concornments; and would <hi>Rule themselves,</hi> and <hi>Please themselves,</hi> according to the <hi>fleshly Appetite and fancy:</hi> and therefore <hi>Love most</hi> the <hi>Pleasures</hi> and <hi>Profits</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> as the provision to satisfie the desires of the <hi>Flesh:</hi> and <hi>God</hi> shall be no further <hi>Loved, Obeyed,</hi> or <hi>Pleased,</hi> than the Love of <hi>Fleshly pleasure</hi> will give leave, nor shall <hi>have</hi> any thing but what the Flesh can spare. This is a <hi>wicked,</hi> a <hi>carnal,</hi> an <hi>ungodly</hi> state; though it break forth in <hi>various</hi> wayes of sinning.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:59498:4"/> V. By this, <hi>Experience it self</hi> may tell you, that <hi>most men</hi> (yea <hi>all,</hi> till Grace renew them) <hi>are in this ungodly miserable state!</hi> (Though only the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> tell us <hi>how</hi> this came to pass.) Though all <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Psalm</hi> 14. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2. 2, 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12, 17, 19. <hi>John</hi> 3. 6.</note> are not Fornicators, nor Drunkards, nor Extortioners, nor Persecutors, nor live not in the same way of sinning; yet <hi>Selfishness</hi> and <hi>Pride, Sensuality</hi> and the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>worldly things, ignorance and ungodliness,</hi> are plainly become the common corruption of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man: so that their <hi>Hearts</hi> are turned <hi>to the world from God;</hi> and filled with impiety, filthiness, and injustice; and their <hi>Reason</hi> is but a servant to their <hi>senses;</hi> and their <hi>mind,</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>life</hi> is <hi>carnal:</hi> and this <hi>carnal mind</hi> is <hi>enmity</hi> to the <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 5, 6, 7.</note>
                     <hi>of God,</hi> and cannot be subject to his Law: This corruption is <hi>hereditary,</hi> and is become as it were <hi>a Nature</hi> to us; being the mortal <hi>malady</hi> of all our Natures: And it is easie to know, that such an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy wicked Nature, must needs be loathsome unto God, and unfit for the happy enjoyment of his love, either here, or in the life to come! For, what commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 4. 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17.</note> hath Light with Darkness?</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. Hence then it is easie to see <hi>what Grace is needfull to a mans salvation.</hi> So <hi>odious</hi> a creature, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 32. 1. 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Titus</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 5, 6, 7, <hi>Heb.</hi> 14. 14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 8.</note> such an unthankfull Rebell, that is turned away from God, and set against him, and defiled with all this filth of sin, must needs be both <hi>Renewed</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, Sanctified</hi> and <hi>Pardoned,</hi> if ever he will be saved. To <hi>Love God</hi> and be <hi>Beloved by him,</hi> and to be <hi>Delighted</hi> herein, in the <hi>sight</hi> of his <hi>Glory,</hi> is the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Happiness</hi> of souls; And all this is <hi>contrary</hi> to an <hi>Unholy State:</hi> Till men have <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Holy Hearts,</hi> they can neither <hi>See</hi> God, nor <hi>Love him,</hi> nor <hi>Delight</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> nor take him for their chief content: For the <hi>Flesh</hi> and <hi>World</hi> have their Delight and Love. And till sin be <hi>pardoned,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3.</note>
                     <hi>God reconciled</hi> to the soul, what <hi>Joy</hi> or <hi>Peace</hi> can it expect from him, whose <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> engageth him to <hi>loath</hi> and <hi>punish</hi> it?</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59498:4"/> VII. And Experience will tell you, how <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient</hi> you are, for either of these <hi>two</hi> works <hi>your selves:</hi> To <hi>Renew</hi> your souls, or to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile</hi> them unto God. Will a Nature that is <hi>carnal,</hi> resist and overcome the <hi>Flesh?</hi> and <hi>abhorr</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 49. 7, 8, 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 21. <hi>Heb.</hi> 14. 12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3.</note> the sin which it most dearly <hi>lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th?</hi> Will a <hi>worldly mind</hi> overcome the <hi>World?</hi> When Custome hath rooted your natural corruptions, are they easily root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up? Oh how great and hard a work is it, to cause a blind unbelieving sinner, to set his heart on another world, and lay up all his Hopes in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? and to cast off all the things he feeth, for that God and Glory which he never saw? And for a <hi>hardened, worldly, fleshly heart,</hi> to become <hi>wise</hi> and <hi>tender,</hi> and <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>heavenly,</hi> and abhorr the sin which it most fondly loveth? And what can <hi>we</hi> do to <hi>satisfie Justice,</hi> and Reconcile such a Rebel-soul to God?</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. Nature and Experience having thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you with your <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>misery,</hi> and what you <hi>want,</hi> will further tell you that God <hi>doth</hi> not yet deal <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17, 24, 27, 28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 19. 20. <hi>Romans</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Job</hi> 33. 14. <hi>to</hi> 25. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 42, 43.</note> with you according to your deserts! He giveth you life, and time, and mercies, when your sin had forfeited all these. He obligeth you to Repent and Turn unto him: And therefore experience telling you, that there is <hi>some Hope,</hi> and that God hath found out <hi>some way</hi> of <hi>shewing mercy</hi> to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath; Reason will command you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of all that are fit to teach you, <hi>what way</hi> of <hi>Remedy</hi> God hath made known. And, as you may soon discover, that the Religion of Heathens, and Mahometans, is so far from shewing the true <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,</hi> that they are part of the <hi>disease</hi> it self; so you may learn, that a wonderfull person, the Lord Jesus Christ, hath undertaken the Office of being the <hi>Redeemer</hi> and <hi>Saviour</hi> of the world, and that he who <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Isaiah</hi> 9. 6, 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 53. <hi>Jobn</hi> 3. 16. 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. 1, 3, 4. <hi>&amp;</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</note> is the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> and Wisdome of the Father, hath wonderfully appeared in the nature of <hi>man,</hi> which he took from the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> being conceived by the <hi>Holy Ghost;</hi> that we might have a <hi>Teacher</hi> sent from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59498:5"/>
                     <hi>Heaven, infallibly</hi> and <hi>easily</hi> to acquaint the world with the <hi>will of God,</hi> and the <hi>unseen things</hi> of life <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 3, 4. <hi>John</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26, <hi>&amp;</hi> 27. <hi>Acts</hi> 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 22, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1, 3, 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 9. 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 10. 12. <hi>John</hi> 5. 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 18, 19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> eternal! How God bare witness of his truth, by abundant, open uncontrolled <hi>miracles:</hi> How he conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Satan, and the world; and gave us an example of perfect Righteousness, and underwent the scorn and cruelty of sinners, and suffered the death of the Cross, as a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for our sins, to <hi>Reconcile</hi> us unto God: How he <hi>Rose again</hi> the third day, and conquered Death, and lived fourty dayes longer on earth, instructing his Apostles, and giving them Commission to Preach the Gospel to all the world, and then ascended bodily into Heaven, while they gazed after him; How he is <hi>now in Heaven</hi> both <hi>God and Man in one person,</hi> the <hi>Teacher,</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>High-Priest</hi> of his Church! Of <hi>Him</hi> must we <hi>learn</hi> the way of life: <hi>By Him</hi> must we be <hi>Ruled</hi> as the Physitianour of souls: All power is given Him in Heaven and Earth: By <hi>his Sacrifice,</hi> and <hi>Merit,</hi> and <hi>Intercession</hi> must we be <hi>pardoned</hi> and accepted with the Father; and only <hi>by him</hi> must we come to God! He hath procured and established a <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> which Baptism is the seal of: even <hi>[That God will in him be our God, and Reconciled Father, and Christ will be our Saviour, and the Holy Ghost will be our Sanctifier, if we will unfeignedly consent; that is, if penitently and believingly we give up our selves to God, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, in these Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.]</hi> This Covenant in the tenor of it, is a Deed of Guift, of Christ, and Pardon, and Salvation to all the world, if by true <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> they will turn to God! And this shall be the Law accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which he will judge all that hear it at the last: For <hi>he</hi> is made the <hi>Judge of all,</hi> and will raise all the dead, and will Justifie his Saints, and judge them unto endless Joy and Glory, and condemn the unbelievers, impenitent and ungodly unto endless misery: The <hi>soul alone</hi> is judged at <hi>Death:</hi> and <hi>body and soul</hi> at the <hi>Resurrection. This Gospel</hi> the Apostles <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>John</hi> 17. 23.</note> Preached to the World; and that it might be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to mens salvation, the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> was first given
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59498:5"/> to inspire the Preachers of it, and enable them to speak in various languages, and infallibly agree in <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23. <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 17, 18. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 5, 6. <hi>John</hi> 3. 5, 6. <hi>Romans</hi> 8. 9.</note> one, and to work many great and open miracles to prove their word to those they preached to: and by this means they planted the Church; which <hi>ordinary Ministers</hi> must <hi>increase,</hi> and <hi>teach,</hi> and <hi>oversee,</hi> to the end of the world, till all the Elect be gathered in. And the same Holy Spirit hath undertaken it, as his work, to accompany this Gospel, and by it to convert mens souls, illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating and sanctifying them; and by a secret Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation to renew their natures, and bring them to that <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Love of God,</hi> which is the Primitive Holiness for which we were created, and from which we fell. And thus by a <hi>Saviour</hi> and a <hi>Sanctifier</hi> must all be <hi>Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> and <hi>Renewed,</hi> that will be <hi>Glorified</hi> with God in Heaven. All this you may learn from the <hi>Sacred Scriptures;</hi> which were written by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 3, 4.</note> of the Holy Spirit, and sealed by mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of open Miracles, and contain the very Image and Superscription of God, and have been received and preserved by the Church, as the certain Oracles of God, and blessed by him through all Generations, to the sanctifying of many souls.</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. When you understand <hi>all this,</hi> it is time for you to <hi>look home,</hi> and understand now <hi>what state your souls are in.</hi> That you <hi>were Made</hi> capable <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Psalm</hi> 4. 4. 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1. 10.</note> of <hi>Holyness</hi> and <hi>Happiness,</hi> you know: that you and all men are <hi>fallen from God</hi> and <hi>Holyness,</hi> and <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness,</hi> unto <hi>Self,</hi> and <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Misery,</hi> you know: that you are <hi>so far Redeemed by Christ</hi> you know, as to have a pardoning and saving Covenant ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered you, and Christ and Mercy offered to your choice. But whether <hi>you are truly penitent belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> and <hi>Renewed by the Holy Ghost,</hi> and so <hi>united unto Christ, this</hi> is the question yet unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved: <hi>this</hi> is the work that is yet to do; without which there is no salvation: And if thou die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59498:6"/> it is done, woe to thee that ever thou wast a man! Except a man be <hi>Regenerate by the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Converted,</hi> and made a <hi>New Creature,</hi> and of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 3. 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Romans</hi> 8. 7, 9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 18, 20.</note>
                     <hi>Carnal</hi> be made <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and of <hi>Earthly</hi> be made <hi>Heavenly,</hi> and of <hi>selfish</hi> and <hi>sinfull</hi> be made <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Obedient to God,</hi> he can never be <hi>saved,</hi> no more than the Devil himself can be saved. And if this be so (as nothing is more sure) I require thee now who readest these words, as thou regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thy salvation, as thou wouldst escape Hell fire, and stand with comfort before Christ and his Angels at the last, that thou <hi>soberly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider</hi> whether <hi>Reason</hi> command thee not▪ to <hi>try thy state,</hi> whether <hi>thou</hi> art <hi>thus Renewed</hi> by the <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of Christ or not? and to call for help to <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 14. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37. <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 30. <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1, 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 7.</note> those that can advise thee, and follow on the search, till thou know thy case? And if thy soul be a stranger to this Sanctifying work, whether Reason command thee not, without any delay, to <hi>make out to Christ,</hi> and <hi>beg his Spirit,</hi> and <hi>cast away thy sins,</hi> and <hi>give up thy self entirely</hi> to thy <hi>God,</hi> thy <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> and enter into his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> with a <hi>full Resolution</hi> never to forsake him? To <hi>deny thy self,</hi> and the desires of the flesh, and this deceitfull transitory world, and lay out all thy Hopes on Heaven! and speedily, what ever it cost thee, to make sure of the Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city which hath no end. And darest thou refuse this when God and Conscience do command it? And further I advise you,</p>
                  <p n="10">X. Understand <hi>how</hi> it is that <hi>Satan hindereth souls from being sanctified:</hi> that you may know how to res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st his wiles. Some he deceiveth by <hi>malitious suggestions,</hi> that <hi>holiness</hi> is nothing but fansié or hypocrisie! (And if <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28, 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. 5, 6.</note> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> were fancies▪ this might be believed.) Some he debaucheth by the power of <hi>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y appetite</hi> and <hi>lust,</hi> so that their <hi>sins</hi> will not let their <hi>Reason</hi> speak Some he keepeth in ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>ignorance,</hi> by the evil education of ignorant
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59498:6"/> Parents, and the negligence of ungodly soul-mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 7. 9. <hi>Hos.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 18, 19. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 13.</note> Teachers: Some he deceiveth by <hi>worldly Hopes,</hi> and keepeth their minds so taken up with worldly things, that the matters of Eternity, can have but some loose uneffectual thoughts, as bad as none: Some are entangled in <hi>evil company,</hi> who make a scorn of a holy life, or feed them with continual diversions and vain delights: And some are so <hi>hardened</hi> in their sin, that they are even <hi>past feeling,</hi> and neither fear Gods wrath, nor care for their salvation, but hear these things as men asleep: and nothing will awake them: Some are discouraged with a conceit that <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> is a life so <hi>grievous, sad,</hi> and <hi>melancholly,</hi> that rather then endure it, they will <hi>venture</hi> their souls, come on it what will (As if it were a <hi>grievous</hi> life, to <hi>Love God,</hi> and <hi>Hope for end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Joyes,</hi> and a <hi>pleasant life</hi> to <hi>Love the world</hi> and <hi>sin,</hi> and live within a step of Hell!) Some that are convinced, do <hi>put off</hi> their conversion <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 3. 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. 43. 44.</note> with <hi>Delayes;</hi> and think its time enough here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and are <hi>purposing</hi> and <hi>promising,</hi> till it be <hi>too late,</hi> and life, and time, and hope be ended. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 8. 39. 8. 42. 44. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 1, 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 29. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 19, 20, 21, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 2, 3, 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 14.</note> And some that see there is a <hi>necessity of Holiness,</hi> are cheated by some <hi>dead opinions,</hi> or <hi>names,</hi> or <hi>Shewes and Images of Holiness:</hi> Either because they hold a <hi>strict opinion:</hi> or because they <hi>joyn</hi> with a <hi>Religious Party;</hi> or because they are of that which they think is the <hi>true Church;</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are <hi>baptized with water,</hi> and observe the <hi>outward parts</hi> of <hi>worship;</hi> and perhaps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they offer God, a great deal of <hi>lip-service,</hi> and <hi>lifeless ceremony,</hi> which never savoured of a holy soul. Thus <hi>deadness, sensuality; worldliness</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisie,</hi> do hinder millions from sanctification and salvation.</p>
                  <p n="11">XI. If ever thou wouldst be saved, <hi>oppress not Reason,</hi> by <hi>sensuality</hi> or <hi>diversions:</hi> but some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 4. 4. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 7. 29.</note>
                     <hi>retire for sober Consideration. Distracted</hi> and <hi>sleepy Reason</hi> is unuseful: <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59498:7"/> a great deal to say to thee; which in a crowd of company and business thou art not fit to hear. It is a dolefull case that a man who hath a <hi>God,</hi> a <hi>Christ,</hi> a <hi>Soul,</hi> a <hi>Heaven,</hi> a <hi>Hell</hi> to think of, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 34. 27. <hi>Isaiah</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 20. <hi>Psalm</hi> 119. 59.</note> will allow them none, but <hi>running thoughts,</hi> and not once in a week bestow <hi>one hour</hi> in man-like <hi>serious Consideration</hi> of them! Sure thou hast <hi>no greater</hi> things to mind. Resolve then sometimes to spend half an hour in the deepest thoughts of thy Everlasting state.</p>
                  <p n="12">XII. Look upon <hi>this world</hi> and <hi>all its Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures,</hi> as a Man of Reason who <hi>forseeth the End,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 29. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 31. <hi>Luk</hi> 12. 19, 20. <hi>John</hi> 14. 1, 2. 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 5. 13.</note> and not as a beast, that liveth but by <hi>sense</hi> on <hi>present objects.</hi> Do I need to tell thee <hi>Man,</hi> that <hi>thou must dye?</hi> Cannot carkasses, and bones, and dust instruct thee, to see the End of Earthly glory, and all the pleasures of the flesh? Is it a <hi>Controversie</hi> whether thy flesh must shortly perish! and wilt thou yet provide for it before thy soul? What a sad farewell must thou shortly take, of all that worldlings sell their souls for! And O how quickly will this be! Alas man, the day is even at hand. A few dayes more, and thou art gone! And darest thou live unready, and part with Heaven for such a world as this?</p>
                  <p n="13">XIII. And then <hi>think soberly of the life to come:</hi> what it is for a soul to appear before the Living God, and be judged to <hi>Endless Joy</hi> or <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12. 7. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 18, 20.</note>
                     <hi>Misery!</hi> If the Devil tempt thee to <hi>doubt</hi> of such a life, remember that <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the <hi>worlds Consent,</hi> and <hi>his own temptations</hi> are witnesses against him. O man, canst thou pass one day, in company or alone, in business or in idleness, without some <hi>sober thoughts</hi> of <hi>Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stingness.</hi> Nothing more sheweth that the hearts of men are <hi>asleep</hi> or <hi>dead,</hi> than that the thoughts of <hi>Endless joy</hi> or <hi>pain, so near at hand, constrain</hi> them not be <hi>Holy,</hi> and overcome not <hi>all</hi> the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>flesh,</hi> as toyes and inconsiderable things.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59498:7"/> XIV. Mark well <hi>what mind most men are of,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 23. 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. 21, 22. <hi>Pro.</hi> 1, 23, 24.</note> when they come to <hi>die!</hi> Unless it be some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate forsaken wretch, do they not all <hi>speak well</hi> of a <hi>Holy life!</hi> and wish that their lives had been spent in the most <hi>fervent Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>strictest obedience</hi> to his Laws! Do they <hi>then,</hi> speak well of <hi>lust</hi> and <hi>pleasures,</hi> and magnifie the wealth and honours of the world! Had they not then rather die as the most <hi>mortified Saints,</hi> than as careless, fleshly, worldly sinners! And dost thou <hi>see</hi> and <hi>know</hi> this, and <hi>yet</hi> wilt thou not be instructed, and be <hi>wise in time?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">XV. Think well, <hi>what manner of men those were,</hi> whose <hi>Names</hi> are <hi>now honoured</hi> for their <hi>Holiness!</hi> What manner of life did Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 29, 30, 31, 33. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 38. <hi>John</hi> 8. 39.</note> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> and all other Saints and Martyrs live? Was it a life of fleshly sports and pleasures! Did they deride or persecute a holy life? Were they not <hi>more strictly holy</hi> than any that thou knowest. And is he not <hi>self condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> that honoureth the <hi>Names</hi> of Saints, and will not imitate them?</p>
                  <p n="16">XVI. Think what the difference is between a <hi>Christian,</hi> and an <hi>Heathen.</hi> You are loath to be Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 15. <hi>Romans</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 34, 35.</note> or Infidels; But do you think a Christian excelleth them but in <hi>Opinion!</hi> He that is not <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> than they, is <hi>worse,</hi> and shall <hi>suffer more</hi> than <hi>they.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">XVII. Think what the difference is between a <hi>Godly Christian</hi> and an <hi>Ungodly.</hi> Do not all the <hi>opposers of Holiness among us,</hi> yet speak for the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 28, 29, 24. 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 28. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 22. <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 29.</note>
                     <hi>same God,</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Scripture,</hi> and profess the <hi>same Creed,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> with those whom they oppose? And is not <hi>this Christ</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of our Holiness, and <hi>this Scripture</hi> the Commander of it? Search and see! whether the difference be not this, that the <hi>Godly</hi> are <hi>serious</hi> in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession; and the <hi>ungodly</hi> are <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> who hate and oppose the <hi>practise</hi> of the very things which <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59498:8"/>
                     <hi>profess;</hi> whose <hi>Religion</hi> serveth but to <hi>condemn</hi> them, while their <hi>lives</hi> are contrary to their <hi>tongues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="18">XVIII. Understand what the Devils policy <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 30. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. 14. 16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5, 6. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 12. 27. 28, 29.</note> is, by raising so many <hi>Sects, and Factions, and Controversies,</hi> about Religion in the world. Even to make <hi>some</hi> think, that they are <hi>Religious,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they can prate for their opinions! or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they think <hi>their party</hi> is the best: Because <hi>their faction</hi> is the <hi>Greatest,</hi> or the <hi>Least,</hi> the <hi>uppermost,</hi> or the <hi>suffering side.</hi> And to turn holy edifying conference into vain wrangling: And to make men Atheists, suspecting <hi>all Religion,</hi> and true to none, because of mens diversity of minds: But remember that <hi>Christian Religion</hi> is but <hi>One;</hi> and a thing easily known by its <hi>ancient Rule;</hi> and the <hi>Universal Church containing all Christians,</hi> is <hi>but one.</hi> And if carnal interest or opinions so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract men, that one party saith, <hi>We are all the Church,</hi> and another saith, <hi>It is we;</hi> (as if the Kitchin were all the House, or one Town or Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage all the Kingdome) wilt thou be mad with seeing this distraction? Hearken sinner! <hi>All these Sects</hi> in the day of Judgement shall concurr as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses against <hi>thee,</hi> if <hi>thou be unholy▪</hi> because however else they differed, <hi>all of them</hi> that are <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stians,</hi> professed the <hi>necessity of Holiness,</hi> and subscribed to that Scripture, which requireth it. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 7, 8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 20. <hi>James</hi> 3. 17.</note> Though thou canst not easily resolve every <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie,</hi> thou maist easily know the <hi>true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> It is that which Christ and his Apostles taught, which all Christians have professed; which Scripture requireth; which is first pure and then peaceable; most spiritual, heavenly, charitable, and just.</p>
                  <p n="19">XIX. Away from that <hi>company</hi> which is <hi>sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. 11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17, 18. <hi>Psalm</hi> 15. 4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 3.</note> and an enemy to <hi>Reason, Sobriety,</hi> and <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> and consequently to <hi>God, themselves</hi> and <hi>thee.</hi> Can they be <hi>wise</hi> for <hi>thee,</hi> that are foolish for <hi>themselves?</hi> or <hi>friends</hi> to <hi>thee</hi> that are undoing <hi>themselves,</hi> or have any pitty on thy soul, when
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59498:8"/> they make a jeast of their own damnation? Will they help <hi>thee</hi> to <hi>Heaven,</hi> who are running so furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to <hi>Hell?</hi> Choose better <hi>familiars,</hi> if thou wouldst <hi>be better.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="20">XX. <hi>Judge not of a Holy life by hearsay:</hi> for it cannot so be known. <hi>Try it</hi> awhile, and then judge <note place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 5. 40. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 29, 30. <hi>John</hi> 6. 35. 37. 45.</note> as thou findest it. Speak not against the things thou knowest not. Hadst thou but <hi>lived</hi> in the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and the <hi>lively belief</hi> of <hi>endless Glory,</hi> and the <hi>delights</hi> of <hi>Holiness,</hi> and the <hi>fears</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> but for one <hi>moneth</hi> or <hi>day,</hi> and with such a <hi>heart,</hi> hadst cast away thy <hi>sin,</hi> and called upon God; and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 19. <hi>Isaiah</hi> 55. 6, 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 33.</note> ordered thy family in a holy manner, especially on the Lords day; I dare boldly say, <hi>experience</hi> would <hi>constrain</hi> thee, to <hi>justifie</hi> a holy life. But yet I must tell thee, it is not <hi>true Holiness,</hi> if thou do <hi>but Try it</hi> with <hi>Exceptions</hi> and <hi>Reserves:</hi> If therefore God hath <hi>convinced</hi> thee that this is <hi>his will and way,</hi> I adjure thee as in his dreadfull <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. <hi>John</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 10. 12. <hi>Psalm</hi> 34. 7. <hi>Psalm</hi> 73. 26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 36. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 3. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. 12.</note> presence, that thou <hi>Delay no longer,</hi> but <hi>Resolve,</hi> and <hi>Absolutely give up thy self to God,</hi> as thy Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, thy Saviour and thy Sanctifier, and <hi>make an everlasting Covenant with him;</hi> and then He and all his Mercies will be thine: His grace will help thee; and his mercy pardon thee: his Ministers will instruct thee, and his people pray for thee, and assist thee: His Angels will guard thee; and his Spirit comfort thee, and when flesh must fail, and thou must leave this world, thy Saviour will then Receive thy soul, and bring it into the participation of his Glory: and he will raise thy body, and justifie thee before the world, and make thee equal to the Angels; and thou shalt <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 27. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. 1. <hi>&amp;</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 25.</note> Live in the sight and Love of God, and in the Everlasting Pleasures of his Glory. This is the end of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holiness.</hi> But if thou harden thy heart, and refusest mercy, everlasting woe will be thy portion, and then there will be no remedy.</p>
                  <p>And now, Reader, I beg of thee, and I beg of God on my bended knees, that these few words may sink in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59498:9"/> thy heart, and that thou wouldst read them over and over again, and bethink thee as a man that must shortly die, whether any deserve thy <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> more than <hi>God?</hi> and thy <hi>thankful remembrance</hi> more than <hi>Christ,</hi> and thy <hi>care</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> more than thy <hi>salvation?</hi> Is there any <hi>felicity</hi> more desirable than <hi>Heaven?</hi> or any <hi>misery</hi> more terrible than <hi>Hell?</hi> or any thing so regardable as that which is <hi>Everlasting?</hi> Will a <hi>few dayes fleshly pleasures</hi> pay for the loss of heaven and thy immortal soul? or will thy <hi>sin</hi> and thy <hi>prosperity</hi> be sweet at death, and in the day of Judgement? As thou art a man, and as ever thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievest that there is a God, and a world to come, and as thou carest for thy soul whether it be saved or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I beseech thee, I charge thee, <hi>think</hi> of these things; <hi>think</hi> of them <hi>once a day</hi> at least! <hi>think</hi> of them with thy most <hi>sober serious</hi> thoughts! <hi>Heaven</hi> is not a <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game!</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> is not a <hi>flea-biting!</hi> Make not a jeast of <hi>Salvation</hi> or <hi>Damnation!</hi> I know thou livest in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted world, where thou maist hear some laughing at such things as these, and scorning at a holy life, and fastening odious reproaches on the godly, and merrily drinking, and playing and prating away their time, and then saying, that they will trust God with their souls, and hope to be saved without so much ado! But if all these men do not change their minds, and be not shortly down in the mouth, and would not be glad to eat their words, and wish that they had lived a holy life, thought it had cost them scorn and suffering in the world, let me bear the shame of a deceiver for ever: But if <hi>God</hi> and thy <hi>Conscience</hi> bear witness against thy <hi>sin,</hi> and tell thee that a <hi>Holy life</hi> is best, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not the gainsayings of a Bedlam world, which is drunk with the delusions of the flesh: But <hi>Give up thy soul and life to God by Iesus Christ in a faithful Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant!</hi> Delay no longer man, but <hi>Resolve; Resove im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately; Resolve unchangeably; and GOD will be thine, and thou shalt be his for ever.</hi> Amen, Lord: Have mercy <hi>on this sinner,</hi> and so let it be Resolved by Thee and him.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>May</hi> 6. 1665.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:59498:9"/>
                  <p> The Second SHEET FOR Poor Families.</p>
                  <p>INSTRUCTIONS FOR A HOLY LIFE.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert White,</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> at the three Daggers in <hi>Fleet-street:</hi> and for <hi>Nevill Simmons,</hi> Book-seller in <hi>Kederminster.</hi> 1665.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59498:10"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59498:10"/>
                  <head>The Second Sheet for Poor Familes: INSTRUCTIONS FOR A Holy Life.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL is not done when men have <hi>begun</hi> a Religious life: All Trees that <hi>blossome</hi> prove not <hi>fruitfull:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Colos.</hi> 1. 23. <hi>Hebrews</hi> 4. 1. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>Matthew</hi> 13. 41. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18. 7.</note> and all <hi>fruit</hi> comes not to <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Many fall off, who seemed to have good beginnings: And many dishonour the Name of Christ, by their scandals and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: Many do grieve their Teachers hearts, and lamentably disturb the Church of Christ, by their ignorance, errors, self-conceitedness, unruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, headiness, contentiousness, sidings and divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59498:11"/> In so much that the <hi>scandals</hi> and the <hi>fewds</hi> of Christians, are the great impediment of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of the <hi>Infidel</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> world, by exposing <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 21. <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 30.</note> Christianity to their contempt and scorn, as if it were but the error of men as unholy and worldly and proud as others, that can never agree among themselves: And many by their passions and selfishness are a trouble to the Families and Neighbours where they live: And <hi>more</hi> by their weaknesses and great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers, are snares, vexations and burdens to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Whereas <hi>Christianity</hi> in its <hi>true constitution,</hi> is a life of such <hi>Holy Light and Love,</hi> such <hi>Purity and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. 8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12.</note>
                     <hi>Peace,</hi> such <hi>fruitfulness</hi> and <hi>Heavenlyness,</hi> as if it were accordingly shewed forth in the lives of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, would command admiration and reverence from the world, and do more to their conversion, than <hi>swords,</hi> or <hi>words alone</hi> can do: And it would make Christians <hi>usefull</hi> and <hi>amiable</hi> to each other; and their l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves a feast and pleasure to themselves. I hope it may prove some help to these excellent ends, and to the securing mens salvation, if in a few sound experienced Directions, I open to you the <hi>Duties</hi> of a Christian life.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Keep still the true form of Christian Doctrine, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and Duty orderly printed on your minds:</hi> that is, <hi>Understand</hi> it clearly and distinctly, and <hi>remember</hi> it. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 14.</note> I mean the great points of Religion contained in Catechismes: you may still <hi>grow</hi> in the clearer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of your Catechismes, if you live an hundred years: Let not the <hi>words only</hi> but the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> be as familiar in your minds, as the rooms of your house are. Such <hi>solid knowledge</hi> will establish you against <hi>seduction</hi> and <hi>unbelief,</hi> and will be <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 13, 14. <hi>Coloss.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 10. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 4.</note> still within you a ready help for every <hi>Grace,</hi> and every <hi>duty,</hi> as the skill of an Artificer is for his work: And for want of this, when you come among <hi>Infidels</hi> or <hi>Hereticks,</hi> their reasonings may seem unanswerable to you, and shake, if not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw your faith: And you will easily erre in <hi>lesser points,</hi> and trouble the Church with your dreams and wranglings. This is the calamity of many Professors;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59498:11"/> that while they will be most censorious Judges, in every controversie about Church-matters, they know not well the Doctrine of the Catechism.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. <hi>Live dayly by faith on Jesus Christ, as the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator between God and you:</hi> Being well grounded <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 3. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3. 17, 18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 22, 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. 6. 16. <hi>Romans</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 33. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 14. 16. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 3, 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 59.</note> in the <hi>Belief</hi> of the Gospel, and understanding <hi>Christs Office: make use of him still in all your wants.</hi> Think on the <hi>Fatherly Love of God</hi> as coming to you <hi>through him</hi> alone: and of the <hi>Spirit</hi> as given <hi>by Him your Head;</hi> and of the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> as <hi>enacted</hi> and <hi>sealed by him;</hi> and of the <hi>Ministery</hi> as <hi>sent</hi> by him; and of all time, and helps, and hope as procured and given by him: When you think of <hi>sin,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity,</hi> and <hi>temptations,</hi> think also of his sufficient pardoning, justifying and victorious <hi>grace.</hi> When you think of the world, the flesh and the Devil, think how <hi>he overcometh</hi> them. Let his <hi>doctrine</hi> and the <hi>pattern</hi> of his most <hi>perfect life,</hi> be alwayes before you as your <hi>Rule.</hi> In all your doubts, and fears, and wants, go <hi>to Him</hi> in the <hi>Spirit</hi> and to the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> by <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>Him alone.</hi> Take him as the root of your <hi>life</hi> and <hi>mercies,</hi> and <hi>Live</hi> as <hi>upon him</hi> and <hi>by his life.</hi> And when you <hi>die,</hi> resign your <hi>souls to Him,</hi> that they may <hi>be with Him where he is, and see his Glory.</hi> To <hi>live on Christ,</hi> and <hi>use Him</hi> in <hi>every want</hi> and address to God, is more then a <hi>General confused believing</hi> in him.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>So Believe in the Holy Ghost, as to Live and work by Him, as the Body doth by the soul.</hi> You are not <hi>Baptised</hi> into his name in Vain: (But too few <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 16. 25. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19 <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2 3, 4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12, 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. 13. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 5, 6.</note> understand the sense and reason of it.) The <hi>Spirit</hi> is sent by Christ for two great works: 1. To the <hi>Apostles</hi> (and <hi>Prophets)</hi> to <hi>inspire them infallibly</hi> to preach the Gospel, and confirm it by miracles, and leave it on record, for following ages in the <hi>Holy Scriptures:</hi> 2. To <hi>all his members,</hi> to <hi>illuminate</hi> and <hi>sanctifie them,</hi> to <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> this Sacred Doctrine (beside his <hi>common guift</hi> to many to <hi>understand</hi> and <hi>preach</hi> it.) The Spirit having first <hi>indited the Gospel,</hi> doth <hi>by it,</hi> first Regenerate, and after Govern all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59498:12"/> true Believers. He is not now given us; for the revealing of new doctrines, but to understand and obey the doctrine revealed and sealed by him long <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15, 16. <hi>Iude</hi> 19, 20. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36. 27. <hi>Isa.</hi> 44. 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14. 20.</note> ago. As the Sun doth by its sweet and secret influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, both give and cherish the natural life of things Sensitive and Vegetative; so doth Christ by his Spirit our spiritual life. As you do no work but by your natural life, you should do none but by your spiritual life: you must not only Believe and Love and pray by it; but manage all your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings by it: For <hi>Holiness to the Lord</hi> must be written upon all: All things are sanctified to you, because you being sanctified to God, devote all to Him, and use all for Him: and therefore must do all in the <hi>strength</hi> and <hi>conduct</hi> of the Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. <hi>Live wholly upon GOD, as All in All: As the first Efficient, principal Dirigent, and Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>l Cause</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 36. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 7, 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 37. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1. 6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4, 5, 6.</note>
                     <hi>of all things.</hi> Let <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> be daily feeding on Him. Let <hi>[Our Father which art in Heaven]</hi> be first inscribed on your hearts, that he may seem most amiable to you, and you may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trust him, and filial Love may be the spring of duty. Make use of the <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> to lead you to the <hi>Father;</hi> and of <hi>Faith in Christ</hi> to kindle and keep alive the <hi>Love of God. The Love of God</hi> is our <hi>Primitive Holiness,</hi> and specially called, with its fruits <hi>[Our Sanctification,]</hi> which <hi>Faith in Christ</hi> is but a <hi>Means to.</hi> Let it be your principal end in <hi>studying Christ,</hi> to see the Goodness Love and Amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness of God in him: A <hi>condemning God</hi> is not so easily loved, as a Gracious Reconciled God. You have so much of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> as you have <hi>Love to God:</hi> This is the proper guift of the Spirit to all the Adopted Sons of God, to cause them with filial af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and dependance, to cry <hi>Abba Father.</hi> Know not, desire not, love not any creature, but purely as subordinate to God! Without <hi>him,</hi> let it be <hi>Nothing</hi> to you; But as the Glass without the face; or scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Letters without the sense; or as the corpse without the soul. Call nothing <hi>Prosperity</hi> or <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> but his Love; and nothing <hi>adversity</hi> or <hi>misery,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 30. 5.</note>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59498:12"/> but his displeasure, and the cause and fruits of it. When any thing would seem <hi>Lovely and desirable</hi> which is <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 63. 3. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 7, 8. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 23. 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3. 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 14.</note>
                     <hi>against him</hi> call it <hi>Dung!</hi> And hear that man as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan or the Serpent, that would entise you from Him: &amp; count him but Vanity, a Worm, and dust, that would <hi>affright</hi> you from your <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>Him. Fear</hi> him much, but <hi>Love him</hi> more! Let <hi>Love</hi> be the soul and <hi>End</hi> of every other duty: It is the end and Reason of all the rest: but it hath no <hi>End</hi> or <hi>Reason,</hi> but its <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi> Think of no other <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> and <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness</hi> of man, but LOVE the final act, and GOD the final object: Place not your Religion in any thing but the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> with its <hi>means</hi> and <hi>fruits. Own</hi> no <hi>grief, desire,</hi> or <hi>joy,</hi> but a <hi>Mourning,</hi> a <hi>Seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and a <hi>Rejoicing Love.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">V. <hi>Live in the Belief, and Hopes of Heaven, and seek it as your part and end; and daily Delight your souls in the forethoughts, of the endless sight and Love of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Col</hi> 3. 1, 2, 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 19, 20, 1. 33. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17, 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 28. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. 23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 18. 20. <hi>Ps.</hi> 73. 25, 26. <hi>Iohn</hi> 18. 36.</note>
                     <hi>God.</hi> As <hi>God</hi> is seen on earth but as in a glass, so is he proportionably enjoyed. But when <hi>mourning, seeking Love</hi> hath done, and <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>enemies</hi> are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and we <hi>behold</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Delights</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> will then be perfect. You may <hi>desire</hi> more on <hi>Earth,</hi> than you may <hi>Hope</hi> for. Look not for a Kingdom of this world, nor for Mount Zion in the wilderness. Christ Reigneth on <hi>Earth,</hi> as <hi>Moses</hi> in the <hi>Camp,</hi> to guide us to the Land of Promise: Our perfect blessedness will be, where the Kingdome is delivered up to the Father, and God <hi>is All in All.</hi> A doubt, or a strange heartless thought of Heaven, is Water cast on the Sacred fire, to quench your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness</hi> and your <hi>Joy.</hi> Can you travel one whole day to such an End; and never think of the place that you are going to? which must be <hi>intended</hi> in every righteous act (either notedly, or by the ready un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>observed act of a potent habit.) When <hi>Earth</hi> is at the best, it will not be Heaven. You live no further by <hi>Faith</hi> like Christians, then you either live <hi>for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> in <hi>seeking</hi> it, or else <hi>upon Heaven</hi> in <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Ioy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">VI. <hi>Labour to make Religion your pleasure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59498:13"/> Look oft to God, to Heaven, to Christ, to the Spirit, to the Promises, to all your mercies; call over your experiences, and think what matter of high De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 1. 2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 84. 2. 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 63. 3. 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37. 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 94. 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119. 47. 70. <hi>Isa.</hi> 58. 14. <hi>Psalm</hi> 112. 1. <hi>Romans</hi> 14. 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. 1, 3, 5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 11, 12. <hi>Psalm</hi> 32. 11.</note> is still before you: And how unseemly it is, and how injurious to your profession, for one that saith be Hopeth for Heaven, to live as sadly, as those that have no higher Hopes than Earth? How should that man be filled with joy, who must live in the joys of Heaven for ever? Especially rejoyce when the mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers of Death, do tell you that your Endless Joy is neer. If <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> with all our mercies in the way, be not Reason enough for a joyful life, there can be none at all. Abhor all suggestions which would make Religion seem a tedious irksome life. And take heed that you represent it not so to others: For you will never make them in Love with that, which you make them not perceive to be delectable and lovely. Not as the Hypocrite, by forcing and framing his Religion to his Carnal mind and pleasure; but bringing up the <hi>heart</hi> to a holy <hi>suitableness,</hi> to the pleasures of Religion.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. <hi>Watch as for your souls, against this flattering tempting world; especially when it is represented as more</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 14. 1 <hi>Ioh</hi> 2. 15, 16. <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. 4, 5. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 4, 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Titus</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 16. 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. 25. <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. 1. 2. 4. <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 26.</note>
                     <hi>sweet and delectable, than God, and Holiness, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> This world with its Pleasure, Wealth, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, is it that is put in the ballance by Satan, against God and Holiness and Heaven: And no man shall have better than he chooseth and preferreth. The bait taketh advantage of the brutish part, when Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is asleep; and if by the help of sense it get the Throne, the Beast will ride and rule the Man; and Reason become a slave to Sensuality. When you hear the Serpent, see his sting: and see Death attending the forbidden fruit. When you are Rising, look down and see how far you have to fall! His <hi>Reason</hi> as well as <hi>faith</hi> is weak, who for such <hi>fool-gawds,</hi> as the pomp and vanities of this world, can forget God and his soul, and death and judgement, Heaven and Hell, yea and deliberately command them to stand by. What <hi>Knowledge</hi> or <hi>Experience</hi> can do good on that man, who will venture so much for such a world, which all that have tryed it call <hi>Vanity</hi> at the last? How deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59498:13"/> then is a worldlings case? O <hi>fear</hi> the world, when it smileth, or seems sweet and amiable. Love it not, if you Love your God and your salvation.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Fly from temptations,</hi> and <hi>crucifie the flesh,</hi> and <hi>keep a constant Government over your appetite and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. 13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Iude</hi> 8. 23. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10: <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. 41. <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 13.</note>
                     <hi>senses.</hi> Many who had no designed stated vice, of worldly interest, have shamfully fallen by the sudden surprize, of <hi>appetite</hi> or <hi>lust.</hi> When custome hath taught these to be <hi>greedy</hi> and <hi>violent,</hi> like a hungry Dog, or a lusting Bore, it is not a sluggish wish or purpose, that will mortifie or rule them! How dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a case is that man in, who hath so greedy a Beast continually to restrain? that if he do but neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his watch one hour, is ready to run him head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into hell? Who can be safe, that standeth long, on so terrible a precipice? The tears and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of many years, may perhaps not repair the loss which one hour or act may bring. The case of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and many another, are dreadful warnings. Know what it is that you are most in danger of; whether <hi>lust,</hi> or <hi>idleness,</hi> or excess in meat, or drinks, or play; and there set the strongest watch for your preservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Make it your daily business to mortifie <hi>that lust;</hi> and scorn that your brutish sense or appetite, should conquer reason. Yet trust not purposes alone; but away from the temptation; Touch not, yea look not on the tempting bait: Keep far enough off, if you desire to be safe. What miseries come from small be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings! Temptation leads to sin, and small sins to greater, and those to Hell! And sin and Hell are not to be played with. Open your sin or temptation to some friend, that shame may save you from the danger.</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. <hi>Keep up a constant skilfull Government, over</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 19. <hi>Iam</hi> 3. 13. 17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>Mat</hi> 5. 5. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. 2, 3. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 5, 6.</note>
                     <hi>your Passions and your Tongues.</hi> To this end, keep a <hi>tender Conscience,</hi> which will smart when in any of these you <hi>sin.</hi> Let <hi>Holy Passions</hi> be well <hi>ordered:</hi> and <hi>selfish carnal passions</hi> be <hi>restrained.</hi> Let your <hi>Tongues</hi> know their <hi>duties</hi> to God and man, and labour to be <hi>skilful</hi> and <hi>resolute</hi> in performing them. Know all the <hi>sins of the Tongue,</hi> that you may avoid them; for your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59498:14"/> innocency and peace do much depend on the prudent <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psalm</hi> 34. 13. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 21.</note> Government of your Tongues.</p>
                  <p n="10">X. <hi>Govern your Thoughts with constant skilful dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</hi> In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, right <hi>Hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> will do most by <hi>enclining</hi> them unto Good. Its <hi>easie,</hi> to Think <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. 9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5. <hi>Psalm</hi> 10. 4. <hi>Psalm</hi> 94. 19. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119. 113. <hi>Prov</hi> 12. 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. 26.</note> on that which we <hi>Love.</hi> Be not unfurnished of <hi>matter</hi> for your Thoughts to work upon! And often <hi>retire</hi> your selves for serious <hi>meditation:</hi> Be not so solitary and deep in musings, as to <hi>over-stretch</hi> your thoughts, and <hi>confound</hi> your minds, or take you off from neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary converse <hi>with others:</hi> But be sure that you be <hi>Considerate,</hi> and dwell much <hi>at home,</hi> and converse most with your <hi>consciences</hi> and <hi>your God!</hi> with whom you have the <hi>greatest</hi> business Leave not your thoughts <hi>unimployed,</hi> or <hi>ungoverned:</hi> scatter them not abroad upon impertinent vanities: O that you knew what daily business you have for them! Most men are wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psal.</hi> 119 59. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 32. <hi>Ier</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 29.</note> deceived and undone, because they are inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate! and dare not or will not retiredly, and soberly use their Reason; or use it but as a slave in chains, in the service of their passion, lust and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests. He was never <hi>wise,</hi> or <hi>good,</hi> or <hi>happy,</hi> who was not <hi>soberly</hi> and <hi>impartially considerate.</hi> How to <hi>be good,</hi> to <hi>do good,</hi> and finally <hi>enjoy good,</hi> must be the summ of all your Thoughts. Keep them first <hi>Holy,</hi> then <hi>charitable, clean</hi> and <hi>chaste.</hi> And quickly check them when they look towards sin.</p>
                  <p n="11">XI. <hi>Let Time be exceeding pretious in your eyes, and carefully and diligently Redeem it.</hi> What haste doth it <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. 16. <hi>Ioh</hi> 14 1, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. 4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 42. 44. <hi>Psalm</hi> 39 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 10. 12.</note> make! and how quickly will it be gone? and then how highly will it be valued, when a minute of it can never be recalled. O what important business have we, for every moment of our Time, if we should live a thousand years! Take not that man to be well in his wits, or to know his God, his End, his work, or his danger, who hath time to spare. Redeem it, not only from <hi>needless sports,</hi> and <hi>playes,</hi> and <hi>idleness,</hi> and <hi>curiosi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y,</hi> and <hi>complement,</hi> and <hi>excess of sleep,</hi> and <hi>chatt,</hi> and <hi>worldliness;</hi> but also from the entanglement of <hi>lesser good,</hi> which would hinder you from greater. Spend
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59498:14"/> Time as men that are ready to pass into another world; where every minute must be accounted for; and it must go with us for ever as we lived here. Let not Health deceive you, into the expectation of living long, and so into a sensless negligence: See your glass running, and keep a reckoning of the expense of Time: and spend it just as you would review it when it is gone.</p>
                  <p n="12">XII. <hi>Let the Love of all in their several capacities, become as it were your very Nature: and doing them all</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5, 6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 10. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. 2. 15, 16. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. 4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Iames</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2. 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 13. 35. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 44, 45. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>Iames</hi> 4. 11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>Titus</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 10, 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 3.</note>
                     <hi>the good you can be very much of the business of your lives. God</hi> must be loved in all his creatures: His <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Image</hi> on <hi>all men;</hi> and his <hi>spiritual Image</hi> on <hi>his Saints.</hi> Our Neighbour must be <hi>Loved</hi> as <hi>Our selves:</hi> that is, our <hi>natural neighbour</hi> as our <hi>natural self,</hi> with a <hi>Love of Benevolence;</hi> and our <hi>spiritual neighbour</hi> as our <hi>spiritual self,</hi> with a <hi>Love of Complacence.</hi> In op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to <hi>complacence,</hi> we may <hi>hate</hi> our sinful <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> as we must <hi>our selves</hi> (much more:) But in opposition to <hi>Benevolence</hi> we must neither hate <hi>our selves, our neighbour,</hi> or <hi>our enemy.</hi> O that men knew how much of Christianity doth consist in <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>doing good?</hi> With what eyes do they read the Gospel, who see not this in every page? Abhorr all that <hi>selfishness, pride,</hi> and <hi>passion</hi> which are the enemies of Love, and those opinions, and factions, and censurings and backbitings, which would destroy it. Take him that speaketh evil of another to you, without a just cause and call, to be Satans messenger, intreating you to hate your Brother, or to abate your Love. For to perswade you, that a <hi>man is bad,</hi> is directly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade you so far to hate him. Not that the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> must be confounded: but Love will call none <hi>Bad</hi> without <hi>constreining evidence.</hi> Rebuke backbiters: <hi>Hurt</hi> no man, and <hi>speak</hi> evil of no man; unless it be not only <hi>just,</hi> but <hi>necessary</hi> to some greater good. Love is lovely: They that Love shall be <hi>beloved. Hating</hi> and <hi>hurting</hi> makes men <hi>Hateful. Love thy neighbour as thy self;</hi> and, <hi>Do as thou wouldst be done by;</hi> are the golden Rules of our duty to men; which must be deeply written on your hearts. For want of this, there
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59498:15"/> is nothing so <hi>false,</hi> so <hi>bad,</hi> so <hi>cruel,</hi> which you may not be drawn to <hi>Think,</hi> or <hi>Say,</hi> or <hi>Do</hi> against your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n▪ SELFISHNES and WANT of LOVE, do as naturally tend to <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Covetousness,</hi> and thence to <hi>cruelty</hi> against all that stand in the way of their desires, as the nature of a Wolf to kill the Lambs. All <hi>factions,</hi> and <hi>contentions,</hi> and <hi>persecutions</hi> in the world, proceed from <hi>selfishness,</hi> and <hi>want of charity. Devouring malice</hi> is the <hi>Devilish</hi> nature. Be as zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in <hi>doing good</hi> to all, as Satans servants are in <hi>hurting.</hi> Take it as the use of all your talents, and use them as you would hear of it at last. Let it be your <hi>business,</hi> and not a matter on the <hi>by:</hi> Especially for <hi>publick good,</hi> and <hi>mens salvation.</hi> And what you cannot do your selves, perswade others to. Give them good Books; and draw them to the means, which are most like to profit them.</p>
                  <p n="13">XIII. <hi>Ʋnderstand the right terms of Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: especially the Unity of the Universal Church, and the Universal Communion which you must hold with</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3. 16. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 41. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 37. 12, 13.</note>
                     <hi>all the parts;</hi> and the <hi>difference between the Church as Visible</hi> and <hi>Invisible.</hi> For want of these, how woful are our divisions? Read oft, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; Eph.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>to</hi> 17. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 21, 22, 23, <hi>Acts</hi> 4 32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. 42. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10, 11, 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3, 4. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5. 12, 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 20 30. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Iames</hi> 3. Study these well. You must have <hi>Ʋnion</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> with all the Christians in the world. And refuse not <hi>local communion</hi> when you have a just call; so far as they put you not on sinning. Let your <hi>usual meeting</hi> be with the <hi>purest Church,</hi> if you law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully may, (and still respect the <hi>publick good.)</hi> But <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. 18. 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 3, 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. 12, 13.</note>
                     <hi>sometimes occasionally</hi> communicate even with <hi>defective faulty</hi> Churches, so be it they are true Christians, and put you not on sin: that so you may shew, that you own them as Christians, though you disown their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. Think not your presence maketh all the faults of Ministry, Worship, or people to be yours (for then I would joyn with no Church in the world.) Know that as the mystical Church consisteth of <hi>Heart-Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> so doth the Church as Visible consist of <hi>Verbal-Covenanters,</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59498:15"/> which make a <hi>credible profession</hi> of <hi>Consent:</hi> And that Nature and Scripture teacheth us to take every mans word as <hi>credible,</hi> till perfidiousness forfeit his <hi>Credit;</hi> which forfeiture must be proved, before any <hi>sober Profession</hi> can be taken, for an insufficient title. Grudge not then at the Communion of any <hi>Professed Christian</hi> in the Church Visible (Though we <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 41.</note> must do our part to cast out the obstinately impenitent by Discipline; which if we cannot do, the fault is not ours.) The presence of hypocrites is no hurt, but oft a <hi>mercy</hi> to the sincere. How small else would the Church seem in the world? <hi>Outward priviledges</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. <hi>Iames</hi> 3. 14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> to <hi>outward Covenanters:</hi> and <hi>inward mercies</hi> to the <hi>sincere▪ Division</hi> is <hi>wounding,</hi> and tends to <hi>death.</hi> Abhor it as you love the Churches welfare or your own: The wisdom from above is, first <hi>pure,</hi> and then <hi>peaceable.</hi> Never seperate what God conjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. It is the <hi>Earthly, sensual, devilish wisdom,</hi> which causeth <hi>bitter envying, and strife, and confusion and every evil work.</hi> Blessed are the Peace-makers.</p>
                  <p n="14">XIV. <hi>Take heed of Pride and Self-conceitedness in</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3. 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 5. <hi>Iames</hi> 3. 1. 17.</note>
                     <hi>Religion:</hi> If once you overvalue your own understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, your crude conceptions, and gross mistakes, will delight you as some supernal light: and instead of having compassion on the weak, you will be unruly and despisers of your Guides, and censorious contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of all that differ from you; and <hi>persecutors</hi> of them if you have power; and will think all intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that take you not as Oracles, and your words as Law. Forget not that the Church hath alwayes suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by censorious, unruly professors on the one hand, (and O what divisions and scandals have they caused!) as well as by the prophane and persecutors on the other. Take heed of both: And when contentions are afoot, be quiet and silent, and not too forward; and keep up a <hi>zeal</hi> for <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">XV. <hi>Be faithfull and conscionable in all your Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. 15.</note> Honour and obey your Parents, and other supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors: Despise not, and resist not Government: If you suffer unjustly by them, be humbled for those sins,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59498:16"/> which cause God to turn your <hi>Protectors</hi> into <hi>Afflicters:</hi> and instead of murmuring and rebelling against them, reform your selves, and then commit your selves to God. Princes and Pastors I will not speak to: Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and servants, and children, must obey their supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors as the Officers of God.</p>
                  <p n="16">XVI. <hi>Keep up the Government of God in your fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: Holy Families</hi> must be chief preservers of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Command.</hi> 4. <hi>Ios.</hi> 24. 15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6, 7, 8. <hi>Daniel</hi> 6.</note> of Religion in the world. Let not the world turn Gods service into a customary lifeless form. Read the Scripture, and edifying Books to them: Talk with them seriously about the state of their souls, and everlasting life: Pray with them fervently: Watch over them diligently: Be angry against sin, and meek in your own cause! Be examples of <hi>Wisdome, Holiness</hi> and <hi>Patience:</hi> And see that the Lords Day be spent in holy preparation for Eternity.</p>
                  <p n="17">XVII. <hi>Let your Callings be managed in Holiness and Laboriousness.</hi> Live not in idleness: Be not <hi>sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Command.</hi> 4. 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3. 10. 12. 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 4. 7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 29.</note> in your work; whether you be bound, or free: In the sweat of your browes you must eat your bread, and labour the six dayes, that you may have to give to him that needeth! slothfulness is sensuality as well as filthier sins. The body (that is able) must have fit employment as well as the soul; or else body and soul will fare the worse. But let all be but as the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of a Traveller, and aim at God and Heaven in all.</p>
                  <p n="18">XVIII. <hi>Deprive not your selves of the benefit of an able faithful Pastor, to whom you may open your case</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 4. 10, 11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. 5. 10. 31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 13.</note>
                     <hi>in secret: or at least of a holy faithful friend: And be not displeased at their free reproofs.</hi> Wo to him that is alone! How blind and partial are we in our own cause! And how hard is it to know our selves without an able faithful helper? You forfeit this great mercy, when you love a flatterer, and angrily defend your sin.</p>
                  <p n="19">XIX. <hi>Prepare for sickness, sufferings, and death:</hi> Overvalue not prosperity, nor the favour of man! If <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 40. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10.</note>
                     <hi>selfish men</hi> prove <hi>false</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> to you, even those of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59498:16"/> whom you have deserved best, marvel not at it; but pray for your <hi>enemies, persecutors</hi> and <hi>slanderers,</hi> that <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 21, 23. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 9. 4, 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 4, 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 4, 8.</note> God would turn their hearts and pardon them. What a mercy is it to be driven from the world to God? When the Love of the world is the greatest danger of the soul? Be ready to die, and you are ready for any thing: Ask your hearts seriously, what is it that I shall need at a dying hour? and let it speedily be got rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and not be to seek in the time of your extremity.</p>
                  <p n="20">XX. <hi>Understand the true method of Peace of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 42. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. 4: <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19, 20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. <hi>Isaiah</hi> 55. 6, 7.</note>
                     <hi>and judge not of the state of your souls upon deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful grounds:</hi> As <hi>presumptuous hopes</hi> do keep men from Conversion, and embolden them in sin; so <hi>causless fears</hi> do hinder our Love and praise of God, by obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Loveliness; And they destroy our <hi>Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and our Delight in God, and make us a burden to our selves, and a grievous stumbling block to others: The <hi>General grounds</hi> of all your comfort, are 1. The Gracious Nature of God: 2. The sufficiency of Christ, and 3. The Truth and Universality of the Promise, which giveth <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> to All if they will Accept him: But this <hi>Acceptance</hi> is the proof of your particular title; without which these do but ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate your sin. <hi>Consent</hi> to Gods Covenant is the true Condition and proof of your title to God as your Father, Saviour and Sanctifier, and so to the saving blessings of the Covenant: which <hi>Consent,</hi> if you <hi>sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive,</hi> must produce the <hi>duties</hi> which you consent to. He that Heartily consenteth, that God be his God, his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 26. 33. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 19, 20, 21. 33. <hi>Coloss.</hi> 3. 1. 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 8. 13.</note> and Sanctifier, is in a state of life. But this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth the rejection of the <hi>world. Much knowledge,</hi> and <hi>memory, and utterance,</hi> and <hi>lively Affections,</hi> are all very desirable! But you must judge your state by none of these; for they are all uncertain: But 1. If <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Holiness</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> have the highest <hi>estimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of your practical judgement, as being esteemed <hi>Best for you;</hi> 2. And be preferred in the <hi>Choice</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution</hi> of your <hi>Wills,</hi> and that <hi>Habitually,</hi> before all the <hi>pleasures</hi> of the world: 3. And be <hi>first and chiefly sought</hi> in your <hi>endeavours;</hi> this is the infallible proof of your sanctification.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59498:17"/>
                  <p> Christian, upon long and serious study and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dare boldly commend these Directions to thee, as the way of God, which will end in Blessedness. The Lord <hi>Resolve</hi> and <hi>Strengthen</hi> thee to obey them.</p>
                  <p>This is the true Constitution of Christianity: This is true Godliness; and this is to be Religious indeed! And all this is no more than to be seriously such as all among us in general words, profess to be. This is the Religion which must difference you from Hypocrites? which must settle you in peace, and make you an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your profession, and a blessing to those that dwell about you! Happy is the Land, the Church, the Family, which doth consist of such as these! These are not they that either <hi>Persecute</hi> or <hi>Divide</hi> the Church; or that make their Religion a servant to their Policy, to their Ambitious designs, or fleshly lusts; nor that make it the bellows of Sedition, or Rebellion, or of an envious hurtful zeal; or a snare for the innocent; or a Pistoll to shoot at the upright in heart: These are not they that have been the shame of their profession, the hardening of ungodly men and Infidels, and that have caused the enemies of the Lord to blaspheme. If any man will make a Religion of, or for his Lusts; of Papal tyranny, or Pharisaical formality, or of his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opinions, or of proud censoriousness, and contempt of others, and of faction and unwarrantable separations and divisions, and of standing at a more observable distance from common professors of Christianity, than God would have them; or yet of pulling up the hedge of Discipline, and laying Christs Vineyard common to the Wilderness; the storm is coming, when this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion founded on the sand will fall, and great will be the fall thereof: When the Religion which consisteth in <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> in <hi>mortifying</hi> the <hi>flesh,</hi> and <hi>crucifying</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> in <hi>Self-denyal, Humility,</hi> and <hi>patience,</hi> in sincere <hi>obedience,</hi> and faithfulness in all <hi>Relations,</hi> in <hi>watchfull self-government,</hi> in <hi>doing good,</hi> and in a <hi>Divine and Heavenly life,</hi> though it will be hated by the ungodly world, shall never be a disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your Lord, nor deceive or disappoint your souls.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>May</hi> 10. 1665.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59498:17"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>